<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The nevv artificial gauging line or rod together with rules concerning the use thereof: invented and written by William Oughtred. who in all due and respective observance præsenteth the same to the Right Honourable LL. Sir Nicolas Rainton Lord Major of London for this præsent yeare, and Ralfe Freeman Alderman Lord Major elect for the yeare now ensuing. and to the Worshipfull George Ethrege the late Master, and Captaine Iohn Miller the præsent Master of the Company of Vinteners. And to the whole body of that right worshipfull societie.</title>
            <author>Oughtred, William, 1575-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1633</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08588</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18901</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113513</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848747</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848747</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13860</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08588)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13860)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1389:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The nevv artificial gauging line or rod together with rules concerning the use thereof: invented and written by William Oughtred. who in all due and respective observance præsenteth the same to the Right Honourable LL. Sir Nicolas Rainton Lord Major of London for this præsent yeare, and Ralfe Freeman Alderman Lord Major elect for the yeare now ensuing. and to the Worshipfull George Ethrege the late Master, and Captaine Iohn Miller the præsent Master of the Company of Vinteners. And to the whole body of that right worshipfull societie.</title>
                  <author>Oughtred, William, 1575-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 40, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Aug. Mathewes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1633.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a final imprimatur and advertisement leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Measuring instruments --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Mensuration --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Wine and wine making --  Gaging and testing --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13860:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13860:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE NEVV ARTIFI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIAL GAVGING LINE OR ROD<hi>:</hi> Together with rules concerning the uſe thereof: Invented and written by WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAM OVGHTRED.</p>
            <p>who In all due and reſpective obſervance praeſenteth the ſame To the Right Honourable LL. Sir NICOLAS RAINTON Lord <hi>Major</hi> of London for this praeſent yeare, and RALFE FREEMAN Alderman Lord <hi>Major</hi> elect for the yeare now enſuing, and To the Worſhipfull GEORGE ETHRAGE the late Maſter, and <hi>Captaine</hi> IOHN MILLER the praeſent Maſter of the Company of <hi>Vinteners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to the whole body of that Right Worſhipfull ſocietie.</p>
            <p>London Printed by <hi>Aug. Mathewes.</hi> 1633.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13860:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13860:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Right Honourable,</hi> and <hi>Right Worſhipfull.</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doubt not, but as every worthy and laudable worke is ſubject to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquie and ill conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: So this my good intent and uſefull invention, which I here preſent unto you Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Lords, and you Right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, into whoſe clientlie I betake both my ſelfe and it, ſhall meet with ſome over-curious and ſupercilious cenſurers, who will miſſe-judge and miſſe-ſay the ſame: though not for the art (againſt which I perſwade my ſelfe they ſhall find little cauſe to except) yet in reſpect of my particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar calling: of the height and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity whereof, ſuch ſmall and low co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations may ſeeme to be unworthy. But may it pleaſe them to conſider,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13860:3"/>
that Theologie is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the chiefe and principall Lady and Miſtreſſe of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faculties; unto which all callings in this life, for their juſt, faithfull, and conſcionable execution, are to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, and bee accountable. And ſeeing God in his ſacred word biddeth not onely <hi>ceaſe to doe evill,</hi> but alſo <hi>learne</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſa. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 16.</note> 
               <hi>to doe well, and ſeeke judgement;</hi> that Divine may bee thought beſt to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme his dutie, that ſhall not onely reprove injuſtice and wrong dealing, but ſhall alſo even in particular acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons informe the conſcience both what is right, and how to performe it. This I have herein endeavoured to effect. The holy Scripture is frequent in ſhewing <hi>the abomination of falſe and deceitful weights,</hi> and in forbidding <hi>to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c. 6. 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ev. 19 35. Prov. 16. 11.</note> 
               <hi>doe unjuſtly in line, in weight, or in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure:</hi> and telleth us that <hi>a true weight, and a juſt balance are of the Lord, and</hi> that <hi>all the weights in the bagge are his worke.</hi> If I therefore by the helpe of God, and the knowledge hee hath beene pleaſed to give me, ſhall exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13860:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
unto this renowned Citie, a line and rule to meaſure veſſels with ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to true art, and ſhall teach how to reforme an errour, which hath for ſome time (through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of better) uſurped the place of truth; and that with much more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility, then it is committed: I hope I ſhall not juſtly be thought to wander out of the limits of my profeſſion and calling. Now the occaſion where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I invented it was this.</p>
            <p>Many yeares agoe, I deviſed for my private uſe an inſtrument, which I <note place="margin">The occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by this gauging in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument was inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> called <hi>the Circles of proportion:</hi> which is nothing elſe but <hi>the Loga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rithmes of Numbers, Sines, and Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents</hi> ſet on circles. And I writ in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine the manifold uſes thereof, not onely in <hi>Arithmetical, Geometrical, and Aſtronomical calculations,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in divers other accounts, practiſes, and queſtions, which are occurrent in the civill ſocietie and converſation of mankind: among which one was concerning <hi>the meaſuring or Gauging</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:13860:4"/>
               <hi>of veſſels:</hi> wherein taking the forme of them to be <hi>ſpharoide, or like a long ſphaere,</hi> with the two ends equally cut off, (as generally both by the ancien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and later writers is ſuppoſed, and in the fabric of ſuch veſſels is ſtill aymed at by the Makers) I delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of the grounds and inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of that moſt admirable Artiſt <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chimedes,</hi> the true and artificiall way of finding their ſeverall contents: and applyed it unto the uſe of that my inſtrument, with as much eaſe and expeditneſſe as I could. Neither did I at all diſcourſe upon the Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall waves practiſed by other men, much leſſe refute any of their errors, but onely barely and poſitively deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the truth. Theſe my notes, and that my inſtrument (after many yeares) at the perſwaſion of a friend of mine, who profered to tranſlate them into Engliſh, I was content hee ſhould ſet out and make common, my ſelfe not having any hand in that publication. When now the tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was ready for the Printer, my
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13860:4"/>
friend having peruſed that which <hi>Maſter Gunter</hi> in his ſecond booke of the <hi>Croſſe ſtaffe Chapt.</hi> 4. writeth very obſcurely about Gauging of veſſels, asked mee what he meant by <hi>the meane Diameter after the vſuall manner?</hi> I anſwered him that in the vſuall manner of art there was no <hi>medium</hi> or meane, but the meane be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the two extreme termes in ſome kind of Proportion: and that all proportion being either <hi>Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, Geometrical, or Muſical,</hi> hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Scholer and an Artiſt, muſt needs (as I thought) by the meane under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand one of thoſe three: and moſt likely the meane arithmetical which is the greateſt of them. For ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the two extreme termes to bee 9 and 4, betweene theſe the meane arithmetical is 61/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, which is halfe the ſumme of both: the meane geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trical is 6: and the meane in muſical proportion is 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>/13. And yet ſaid I, the meane arithmetical is too little, as in the menſuration of tapering timber I proved: much more either of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13860:5"/>
two reſt. And other meane diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which may give the true content of a ſphaeroides, art affordeth none. My friend replyed, Maſter <hi>Gunter</hi> is generally acknowledged to have bin a man of skill, and you utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne: and hee that ſhall find your booke diſagreeing from his docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, will without any more adoe reject it; you ſhall therefore doe well to write in a few lines why you differ from M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Gunter,</hi> and to ſhew that his way by the meane diameter cannot ſtand with art. Which his counſell I ſeeing not to be unneceſſary, eſpecially in regard of the great paines hee had taken in the tranſlation of my notes, tooke a pen, and preſently in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine of his tranſlation writ that ſhort advertiſement touching M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Gunters</hi> meane diameter.</p>
            <p>Not long after that tranſlation was in print, word was ſent me into the countrey, that an old man (that ſaid he was) <hi>the Gauger of London</hi> came earneſtly inquiring after me, and was very angry; profeſſing <hi>hee would vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:13860:5"/>
               <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Gunters credit, and ſpeake for him, that could not anſwer for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: and that I had taught a falſe way of Gauging veſſels: and that both hee and many others, had bought of my bookes;</hi> which much troubled him: and hee was very ſolicitous <hi>how they ſhould come by their money againe: and that hee never ſaw ſuch a booke in his life; for he could not tell what to make of it.</hi> The tranſlator told him, that when he, or any other for him, ſhould diſprove that way of meaſuring veſſels, which I had delivered; let him bring his booke, and he ſhould have his money againe for it.</p>
            <p>At my next comming to London, hee hearing of my being in towne, came to mee, and expoſtulated with me, <hi>why I would preſume to queſtion any thing that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Gunter writ?</hi> I anſwered him, that it is a fault inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the ſtudents of theſe arts, to be very incredulous, eſpecially if they ſee demonſtration to the contrary. Hee ſaid <hi>I underſtood not what M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Gunter meant by the meane diameter</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:13860:6"/>
               <hi>after the vſuall manner: For Mr.</hi> Gunter <hi>(though hee ſaid not ſo much) did underſtand the manner vſuall in London; and that hee him ſelfe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in gauging: which was to halfe the ſumme of the diameters at the head and bung, and to adde one quarter of their difference: and that this was a true way, and a better way then mine: and that if hee ſhould uſe my way, it would require much more paines, and longer time: and that hee had a man, whom hee had taught, which had little or no skill in Arithmetic, and could ſcarce multiply, yet in his way hee ſhould gauge with any man in England; and that if that his way were not right, hee might doe more wrong in a few yeares then any Aldermans ſtate in London is worth; and that hee was ſworne to doe juſtly.</hi> I anſwered, that the greater tye lay upon him to doe juſtly, and the more hurt hee might doe by miſgauging, the more thankes hee owed mee, for ſhewing him the right; and with the more gladneſſe hee ſhould em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it, notwithſtanding it might
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13860:6"/>
have ſome more difficultie: for though I ſhould hold my peace (as Mr. <hi>Gunter</hi> it ſeemeth did) yet hee were never the more juſtifiable: and wiſhed him to looke to his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: eſpecially ſeeing now hee might informe himſelfe in the truth. Hee ſaid <hi>hee found indeed by his expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that the adding of a quarter of the difference was ſomewhat too much; and therefore that now hee began to take one fift part thereof: and yet both wayes were better then mine; and hee would not learne of mee to gauge veſſels.</hi> And ſo went his way in great choler and diſpleaſure. I did indeed wonder at that his aſſertion; that whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee tooke the quarter, or the fift part of the difference, yet both are better then the way of art, which I had delivered: for even in that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, which in my booke is ſet downe, of a veſſel having the diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at the bung 32 inches, and the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter at the head 18 inches, and the length 40 inches; had hee but made triall, hee ſhould have found the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13860:7"/>
content computed by one quarter of the difference, to have beene gallons 110 and almoſt an halfe; and by one fift part, to have beene gallons 1051/10; whereas the true meaſure by art is gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons 107<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and an halfe and ſomewhat better; which is almoſt in the very midſt betweene both: ſo that if any man will ſuppoſe one of his wayes, bee it the former, or the latter, to bee right: yet the other muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie bee further from the truth, then that which I taught; becauſe it fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling betweene both, muſt needs bee neerer to each, then one of them is to the other.</p>
            <p>Not long after M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Elias Allen</hi> (a man well knowne and eſteemed by all men of art for his skilfulneſſe in making inſtruments in metal) being in the company of ſome gentlemen of good quality and worth, upon occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on related theſe former words of the Gauger, what great detriment hee might doe by his manner of Gauging, if it were not true. Which his ſpeech M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>George Ethrege,</hi> then Maſter of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13860:7"/>
the right worſhipfull Company of <hi>Vinteners,</hi> hearing and obſerving, ſaid that indeed he doubted not, but there was much wrong done by miſgauging wine veſſels; and that many times they found it to their coſt; but they could not eaſily remedy it. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore invited M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Allen</hi> to requeſt me to deviſe <hi>a Gauging inſtrument,</hi> which might be according to true art, and of familiar and eaſie performance; that they might examine and try their veſſels themſelves: and ſaid it would bee an invention very acceptable, and of great uſe, and a meanes to prevent much wrong that many times is done. Which inquiſition and ſtudie, to find out a true and perfect inſtrument for meaſuring of veſſels (though at firſt without any hope of effecting any ſingular thing therin after ſuch a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of learned artiſts, and writers in this kind, with the meaneſt of which I am not to bee compared) I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke, merely our of my love to the ſociety of mankind, and my deſire of advancing truth and juſtice; and at
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13860:8"/>
laſt by the helpe of God, who is righteous, and loveth righteouſneſſe, have brought to paſſe: And herein withall humble and affectionate ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceableneſſe, both unto you my <hi>right honourable LL.</hi> upon whom the principall care of all ſuch admenſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions within this moſt flouriſhing and illuſtrious Citie doth reſt, and of you <hi>right worſhipfull the Maſters and whole Company of Vintners,</hi> and to as many of this moſt renowned Citie as ſhall have cauſe to uſe the ſame, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent this my <hi>new gauging inſtrument.</hi> Onely deſiring thus much, that you would be pleaſed to vouchſafe it your acceptance with the ſame loving and benevolent reſpect, as I my ſelfe had unto you, and the truth, in the inveſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation thereof.</p>
            <p>Neither indeed may I omit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the noble favour that <hi>the right</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The tryall made of this gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it.</note> 
               <hi>worſhipfull Company of Vintners</hi> did afford, though unknowne, unto mee. For when Mr. <hi>Elias Allen</hi> had fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed up one of thoſe my <hi>inſtruments</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:13860:8"/>
               <hi>or gauging rods,</hi> and had brought it to their Hall, they preſently deputed certaine of their ſociety to ſee the experience and performance thereof, at the Taverne by <hi>Leaden-hall</hi> under the ſigne of the <hi>Kings-head:</hi> and they tooke the paines to examine the truth of it in many and ſundry kinds of wine veſſels; where, as I have beene told (for I was not there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent my ſelfe) beyond all expectation they found ſuch an exact agreement with the meaſure of water they filled in by gallons, after the ſealed Standard for wine meaſure, that in moſt the difference was ſcarce ſenſible; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the markes ſet thereupon exceeded the ſame meaſures by two or three, and ſometimes more then foure gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons in a veſſell. Whereupon they agreed with Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> for a price, and beſpake of him threeſcore of the ſame my <hi>rods or inſtruments.</hi> Which ſo noble and courteous reſpect unto me, to decree the examination of that my invention (though other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit or recompenſe for the ſame
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13860:9"/>
I demand none) I cannot but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge with much thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>Neither is the facilitie of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <note place="margin">The facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by this new rod, compared with the trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeneſſe of the other erroneous way.</note> therewith any whit inferior to the certaintie of it: but even in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring of veſſels by this true rule much leſſe paines is taken, then that other erroneous and inartificial way doth neceſſarily require.</p>
            <p>For therein <hi>firſt the two diameters at the bung, and at the head meaſured in ynches muſt be added together, and halfe the ſumme of them taken and kept.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly the diameter at the head is to bee ſubducted out of the diameter at the bung, and the remaines to bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided by</hi> 4, <hi>or elſe by</hi> 5, <hi>to find out the quarter, or fift part of their difference.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly that quarter of fift part of the difference muſt bee added to the halfe ſumme kept; to make up a meane diameter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly there remaineth a proportion to bee wrought by multiplication and diviſion; which is this,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:13860:9"/>
               <hi>As the quadrate of</hi> 17<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>15 <hi>(which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Gunter calleth his gauge point) is to the quadrate of the meane diameter laſt found,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So is the length of the veſſell meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in inches, to the content of the ſame veſſell in wine gallons.</p>
            <p>Such a deale of paines, and ſuch a multiplicitie of worke is undergone in their ordinary gauging: and yet when all is done, the capacitie or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the veſſell ſo found is merely conjectural, ſometimes falſer and ſometimes truer, according as the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meters of the veſſell are more or leſſe unequall.</p>
            <p>But this way of art, which I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, beſides that it is conſtant and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall in all kinds of wine veſſells, is moſt eaſily performed only with one ſingle addition &amp; multiplication; as ſhall anon bee declared both by rule, and examples. Soe that now I hope I have made <hi>Mr Gauger</hi> amends for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13860:10"/>
the too much difficultie and paines hee thought my booke put him to; and that henceforth hee will bee as earneſt to vindicate my credit alſo, as hee hath egerly traduced it before he rightly knew me. For although I cannot ſo well excuſe his raſhneſſe in impertinent interpoſing himſelfe in queſtions hee had ſmall skill in: yet I perſwade my ſelfe he had no malice againſt my perſon, who was then ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly unknowne to him. And for my part (for ought I remember) I had not ſo much as heard of any ſuch offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer about the Citie. But I wholly impute his offence at me partly to the high eſtimation hee had of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> from whom to diſſent he thought to be a hainous matter: and partly to his diſſidence and diſtruſt of my rule, how it might hold when it came to tryal. And therefore I doe willingly returne againe into favour with him, and recommend this my invention and my ſelfe to his future approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and friendſhip; aſſuring him that what I have before written was not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13860:10"/>
intented againſt him: but onely to ſhew the true occaſion how I fell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this ſearch and diſquiſition: which in regard of my profeſſion ſeemed to bee very neceſſary.</p>
            <p>The principles whereon the way <note place="margin">Two prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples or grounds of this gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> that I teach is grounded, are theſe two. Firſt that a wine veſſell is in forme of a perfect ſphaeroide with the two ends equally cut off. The truth of which ground appeareth both by the generall conſent of almoſt all who have written of gauging: and by the fabric of ſuch kind of veſſels; which by the workemen and makers thereof (ſo farreforth as in practiſe they are able) are intended to bee ſuch. And now lately by tryal made thereof with the Standard, whereunto it is found to hold greater correſpondence in all kind of thoſe veſſels, then could bee hoped for, or almoſt imagined.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that a <hi>ſphaere, or ſpharoide</hi> containeth two third parts of <hi>a cylin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> hauing the ſame length and thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and conſequently that the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13860:11"/>
convexitie betweene two <hi>cylin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> one within the <hi>ſphaeroide,</hi> and the other without touching it, and having the ſame center and height, is equall to two third parts of the difference of thoſe two <hi>cylinders:</hi> which hath long ſince beene taught by the ancient <hi>Siracuſan Archimedes</hi> in his firſt booke of <hi>the Sphaere and Cylinder,</hi> &amp; in his booke of <hi>Cone-like and ſphaere-like</hi> magnitudes: &amp; of late by our Engliſh <hi>Archimedes</hi> Mr <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Briggs,</hi> in his Treatice of <hi>Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica logarith mica.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Out of the conſideration of theſe two principles, or grounds, I framed my rule, which I ſet downe in my booke of <hi>the Circles of proportion,</hi> Chapt. 9. in theſe words. <hi>Meaſure</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The rule of Gauging framed out of thoſe tvvo grounds.</note> 
               <hi>the two diameters of the veſſell, in yn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or elſe in tenth parts of a foot, the one at the bung hole, the other at the head, and alſo the length within. And by the diameters found, find out the circles; then adde together two third parts, of the greater circle, and one</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:13860:11"/>
               <hi>third part of the leſſe; Laſtly, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the aggregate by the length: ſo ſhall you have the content of the veſſell, either in cubic ynches, or cubic tenth parts of a foot.</hi> Which afterward in the end of that Chapter (having firſt inquired the quantity of a gallon both Ale, and Wine meaſure in ſolid yn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, the one to bee 272¼ the other 231) I taught how to reduce into gallons and hundreth parts, by divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the whole number of ynches contained in the veſſell by either of thoſe two numbers reſpectively. And this is that very rule, the worke and practice of which I have by art, with an invention not yet thought upon by any other, and with diviſions calcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for that purpoſe, ſitted and apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to this my <hi>new gauging line or rod.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It conſiſteth of <hi>two rulers of braſſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging rod deſcribed: and of the ſeverall parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</note> about 32 ynches of length, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo are halfe an ynch broad, and a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an ynch thick: that being ſet together they may make halfe an ynch ſquare.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13860:12"/>
At one end of both thoſe rulers are <hi>two little ſockets</hi> of braſſe faſtned on ſtrongly: by which the rulers are held together, and made to move one upon another, and to bee drawne out unto any length, as occaſion ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire: and when you have them at the juſt length, there is upon one of the ſockets <hi>a long Scrue-pin</hi> to ſerue them faſt.</p>
            <p>Theſe two little ſockets encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe not both rulers quite round: but have each of them <hi>a ſlit about a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of an ynch board:</hi> that they may not hinder the ſight of the diviſions, which are upon the broad or flat ſides of the rulers. Which diviſions are indeed of moſt principall uſe: being properly the <hi>gauge-diviſions:</hi> and are now firſt of all invented, and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated to the menſuration of veſſels.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The gauge-diviſions</hi> are in all two hundred and thirtie: of which eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular diviſion ſtandeth for one hundreth part of a wine gallon: ſo that they are in all a wine gallons
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13860:12"/>
and 30 hundred parts. And for the more perſpicuous diſtinguiſhing of them they are figured by tens thus, 0<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>10, 0<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>20, 0<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>30, 0<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>40, 0<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>50, 0<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>60, 0<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>70, 0<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>80, 0<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>90, 1<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>00, 1<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>10, 1<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>20, 1<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>30, 1<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>40, 1<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>50, 1<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>60, 1<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>70, 1<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>80, 1<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>90, 2<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>00, 2<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>10, 2<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>20, 2<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>30: there being betweene e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of thoſe figures ten divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, or ten hundreth parts.</p>
            <p>At the other end of both the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers is <hi>a hooke framed into right or ſquare angles</hi> to be ſcrued on: the one with <hi>a Scrue-pin,</hi> the other with <hi>a matrix or Scrue-plate.</hi> And above theſe hookes the edge of both ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers is divided into ynches, beginning exactly equall with the ends of the hookes: and figured with 5, 10, 15, 20, 25, 27, 30, &amp;c. And each ynch is ſubdivided into ten equall parts. Which diviſion of ynches, together with the hookes, ſerve to take the length of all veſſels; that the ends of the barrell boards overreaching the bottoms, may not bee an impediment to the meaſuring thereof.</p>
            <p>Vpon the other edge of each ruler
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13860:13"/>
is ſet the <hi>the line of Numbers:</hi> which is the very ſame in both<hi>:</hi> though ſome what differently figured. For that on the ruler next the <hi>ſocket with the long Scrue-pin,</hi> is noted with the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 20, which I therefore call <hi>the line of digit num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers:</hi> and that on the other ruler is figured with tens, as 10, 20, 30, 40, 50, 60, 70, 80, 90, 100, 200, 300: and I call it <hi>the line of denarie numbers.</hi> Wherein you are to remember that from 1 to 5, and from 10 to 50, and alſo above 100, every ſpace is ſubdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into one hundred parts, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 5 unto 10, and above 50 unto 100, becauſe the ſpaces are too ſmall to receive an hundred parts, they are ſubdivided but into fiftie.</p>
            <p>Thus having ſhewed the deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">The uſe of the gauging rod taught in foure rules.</note> of the ſeverall parts of the <hi>gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging rod:</hi> I now come to the uſe thereof in meaſuring any kind of veſſel by the wine gallon. For which I will ſet downe theſe fower rules,</p>
            <div n="1" type="rule">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:13860:13"/>
               <head>Rule I. <hi>How to take the length of a Veſſell.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HAving firſt ſitted the two hookes upon the ends of the two rulers, ſo that the line of ynches may be uppermoſt, draw out the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers in length, and apply them to the veſſell long wiſe, ſo that the two hookes may embrace the two bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms thereof: at that length ſcrue them faſt together with the long Scrue-pin in the ſocket: then take off the hooke, which hath the Scrue-pin: and looke how many ynches the ſoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket of the ruler which hath the hooke on doth cut in the ruler with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the hooke: for that ſhall be the length of the veſſell from out ſide to out ſide in ynches: wherefore if out of that meaſure you take the thicknes of the two bottoms (which may bee eaſily eſtimated by a ſpigot hole) you ſhall have the true length of the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell within.</p>
               <p>But if the length of the veſſell be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13860:14"/>
leſſe then 27 ynches, you cannot uſe both hookes, as before was done. Wherefore apply the ruler which hath the matrix or Scrue-plate to the veſſell, ſetting that hooke againſt one of the bottoms: and where the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions of ynches in that ruler begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, ſtick up a knife<hi>:</hi> then remove that ſame hooke to the other bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome; and the ynches, which the knife cutteth, ſhall give the length of the veſſell from out ſide to outſide.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="rule">
               <head>Rule II. <hi>How to take the Diameters of a Veſſell at the Bunge, and at the Head. and how to adde them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that you may finde the ſumme of them.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Diameters are not meaſured by ynches, as the length is, but by Wine gallons, and hundreth parts: in this maner. Take off the hook which hath the ſcrue-pinne, and dipp that end of the Ruler into the Veſſell at the bung; and looke how many parts of the diviſions of Gallons the inſide
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13860:14"/>
of the bung-hole doth cut, the ſame ſhall bee the Diameter at the bung. In like maner apply the ſame end of the Ruler to the head of the Veſſell without; and looke how many parts of the diviſions of Gallons it is broad over the midd'ſt or center thereof; the ſame ſhall be the Diameter at the head.</p>
               <p>But if the Diameter at the bung be greater then that Ruler is long: draw out the rulers, and ſcrue them at their whole length: and ſo meaſure there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Diameters, as was before ſhewed.</p>
               <p>The two Diameters being found out muſt bee added together, thus: Write downe the Diameter at the bung twice, and under it the Diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at the head onely once, ſetting like places one under another in the ſame rowes: that is all the unites in one rowe; all the tenth parts (which are they next the units) in another row; and all the hundreth parts in the laſt row: and draw a long line be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the unites and the parts, then
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13860:15"/>
adde them all three together into one ſumme by the way of ordinary Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. As in example; Suppoſe a Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel that hath the diameter at the bung gallon 1 &amp; 8 hundreth parts, <hi>viz.</hi> 1<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>08; and the diameter at the head onely 96 hundreth parts of a Gallon, <hi>viz.</hi> 0<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>96. you ſhall write downe <gap reason="math">
                     <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Diameter at the bung twice, &amp; the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter at the head once and adde them altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as you ſee done in the ſide: and the ſumme of the diameters ſhall bee found 3<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>12, that is gallons 3 and 12 hundreth parts. And thus ſhall you doe in all Veſſels.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="rule">
               <head>Rule III. <hi>How to multiply the ſumme of the Diameters of a Veſſell by the length.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe length of a Veſſell being mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured in ynches and tenth parts, and the Diameters being found out in Gallons and hundreth parts, and alſo added together, as hath beene decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red:
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13860:15"/>
The ſumme of the Diameters is to bee reconed in the line of digit numbers, which is noted with the figures 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, &amp;c. and the length, in the other line of denarie numbers, which is noted with the figures 10, 20, 30, 40, 50, &amp;c. In both which lines of numbers you are to conſider, that in the ſpaces betweene the figures e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very tenth diviſion is diſtinguiſhed with a long line: and every ſingle di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion with a ſhort line: and every fift with a line of a length betweene both<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and in the line of digit num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, they ſignifie ſo many hundreth parts of a gallon: But in the line of denarie numbers (as alſo in the line of digit numbers beyond 10) every tenth diviſion is for unites; and every ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle diviſion is for tenth parts. and beyond 100 every tenth diviſion is for ten; and every ſingle diviſion for one unite. Where note, that in thoſe ſpaces, which by reaſon of their ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe have but 50, yet they are under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to bee 100, by imagining every one to containe two.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:13860:16"/>
The nature and valuation of both the lines of numbers, the digit and the denarie, being underſtood, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplication is thus to be wrought. Set the unite place of the line of digit numbers marked with 1, to the place of the length of the Veſſell reconed in the line of denary numbers: there ſcrue the Rulers faſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then in the line of digit numbers recon the ſumme of the Diameters found out, that at the Bung being doubled, as was taught before: and looke what ſpace and diviſion it poynteth out in the line of denary numbers<hi>:</hi> the ſame being rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably aeſtimated, ſhall bee the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct ſought for.</p>
               <p>By aeſtimating reaſonably I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that you conſider whether the figure of that ſpace is to bee taken for tenns or for hundreds: which is done very eaſily: for no man is ſo ſimple, as to miſtake a Veſſell of ten or twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Gallons, for one or two hundred; or of one or two hundred gallons, for one of ten or twenty. And yet this ſhort rule may bee given. That the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13860:16"/>
product is to bee aeſtimated according to that former valuation of the line of denarie numbers: unleſſe the Veſſell be ſo ſmall, that the ſumme of the diameters amount not to one gallon: for then the figures 100 &amp; 200, are to be taken for 10 and twenty.</p>
               <p>And if at any time it chance, that the ſumme of the diameters falleth not betweene the unite place in the line of digit numbers, and the ſocket: divide the ſame ſumme by 2, and then multiply the one halfe by the length; ſo ſhall you have halfe the product ſought for: which being doubled will give you the whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="rule">
               <head>Rule IIII. <hi>How to gauge or meaſure the content of any Veſſell in Wine gallons.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TAke the length of the Veſſell pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in ynch-meaſure, according to the <hi>Rule</hi> I, then take the two di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ameters in gallon meaſure, and adde them together, that at the bung being doubled, according to the <hi>Rule</hi> II.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13860:17"/>
Laſtly multiply the ſumme of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ameters by the length, according to <hi>Rule</hi> III: and the product being rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably aeſtimated, ſhall give the number of Wine gallons contained in that Veſſell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="examples">
               <head>The performance and practice of this Worke by Examples.</head>
               <div n="1" type="example">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Example</hi> I.</head>
                  <p>ANd firſt I will take the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <note place="margin">Diverſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples ſhewing the uſe of this Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the practice of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer rules.</note> in my booke of the <hi>Circles of Proportion, Chap</hi> 9, of a Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell ſuppoſed to bee in length 40 yn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; and the diameter at the bung 32 ynches; and the diameter at the head 18 ynches: which two diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters being taken with my gauging rod in gallon meaſure, would have beene at the bung gallons 1 and 16 hundreth parts, and at the head almoſt 37 hundreth parts of a gallon. Set downe the diameter at the bung twice, and the diameter at the head once, &amp; adde them: the ſumme of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13860:17"/>
diameters ſhall be gallons 2 &amp; almoſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9 hundreth parts, by <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Rule</hi> II. which being multiplyed by 40, the product ſhal be gallons 107, and better then an halfe; which is the true content ſought for.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="example">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Example</hi> II.</head>
                  <p>Suppoſe a ſmall Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell; whoſe length is ynches 45 and 3 tenth parts, <hi>viz.</hi> 45<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>3; and the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter at the bung 38 hundreth parts of a gallon; and the diameter at the head 30 hundreth parts. what is the content?</p>
                  <p>Adde the two dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meters <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap> together, that at the bung being dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, the ſumme is gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons 1 and 6 hundreth parts, by <hi>Rule</hi> II. Multiply this ſumme by the length 45<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>3: and the product ſhall bee 48<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by <hi>Rule</hi> III, that is gallons 48 and almoſt 12 hundreth parts: which is the true content ſought for.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="example">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:13860:18"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Exam.</hi> III.</head>
                  <p>Suppoſe another ſmall veſſel, whoſe length is ynches 30 and 7 tenth parts, <hi>viz.</hi> 30<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>7. and the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter at the bung 34 hundreth parts of a gallon: and the diameter at the head 28 hundreth parts, what is the content?</p>
                  <p>Adde the two diameters together, that at the bung being doubled: the ſumme is onely 96 hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap> parts of a gallon, by <hi>Rule</hi> II. Multiply this ſumme by the length 30<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>7: and the product ſhall be 29<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>47, by <hi>Rule</hi> III, that is gallons 29, and 47 hundreth parts, which is almoſt an halfe. which is the true content. For the firſt figure 2 ſignifyeth not 200 (though it be ſo marked on the line of denarie numbers) but only 20; as both plaine reaſon, &amp; alſo the ſhort rule, at the end of <hi>Rule</hi> III, wil ſhew.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="example">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Exam.</hi> IIII.</head>
                  <p>Suppoſe a great veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell: whoſe length is ynches 70 and an halfe, <hi>viz.</hi> 70<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>5; and the diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13860:18"/>
at the bung gallons 2 and 3 hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth parts, <hi>viz,</hi> 2<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>03; and the diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at the head gallons 1 and 10 hundreth parts, <hi>viz.</hi> 1<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>10. what is the content?</p>
                  <p>Adde the two diameters together, that at the bung being doubled; the ſumme is gallons 5 and <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 16 hundreth parts, by <hi>Rule</hi> II. Multiply this ſumme by the length 70<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>5: but becauſe the unit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> place of the line of digit numbers, being ſet to 70<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>5 in the line of denarie num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, the ſumme of the diameters 5<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>16 will over-reach beyond the ſocket: therefore to helpe this, take halfe the ſumme of the diameters, <hi>viz.</hi> gallons 2<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>58: and multiply that halfe ſumme by the length 70<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>5: and the product ſhall bee 181<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, by <hi>Rule</hi> III, that is gallons 181 and almoſt 9 tenth parts: which is halfe the true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. And being doubled ſhall give gallons 363<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>78 for the whole content of that great veſſell.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:13860:19"/>
The Examples following are of ſome veſſels meaſured in the preſence of them, which were deputed by the Company of Vinteners to ſee the try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of this Gauging line or rod.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="example">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Exam.</hi> V.</head>
                  <p>A Canarie pipe whoſe length was ynches 48 and an halfe, <hi>viz.</hi> 48<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>5; and the diameter at the bung 93 hundreth parts of a gallon, <hi>viz.</hi> 0<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>93: and the diameter at the head 54 hundreth parts, <hi>viz.</hi> 0<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>54. what is the content?</p>
                  <p>Adde the two diameters together, that at the bung being <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap> doubled, the ſumme is gallons 2 and 4 tenth parts, by <hi>Rule</hi> II. Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply this ſumme by the length 48<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>5: and the product ſhall bee 116<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>4 by <hi>Rule</hi> III, that is gallons 116 &amp; 4 tenth parts: which is the content ſought for.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="example">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Examp.</hi> VI.</head>
                  <p>A Graves-hogſhead whoſe length was ynches 31 and 2 tenth parts, <hi>viz.</hi> 31<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>2: And the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter at the bung 73 hundreth part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of a gallon, <hi>viz.</hi> 0<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>73; and the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13860:19"/>
at the head 57 hundreth parts, <hi>viz.</hi> 0<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7. What is the content?</p>
                  <p>Adde the two dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meters <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap> together, that at the bung being doubled, the Summe is gallon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and 3 hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth parts, by Rule II. Multiply this ſumme by the length 31<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>2: and the product ſhall bee 63<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>34 by Rule III, that is gallons 63 and 34 hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth parts: which is the content ſought for.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="example">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Example</hi> VII.</head>
                  <p>A High-countrey hogſhead whoſe length was ynches 30, and 82 hundreth parts, <hi>viz.</hi> 30<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>82: And the diameter at the bung 63 hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth parts of a gallon: <hi>viz.</hi> 0<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>63 and the diameter at the head 51 hundreth parts, <hi>viz.</hi> 0<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>51. What is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent?</p>
                  <p>Adde the two diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <gap reason="math">
                        <desc>〈 math 〉</desc>
                     </gap> together, that at the bung being doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, the ſumme is gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons 1 and 77 hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13860:20"/>
parts, by Rule II. Multiply this ſumme by the length 30<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>82: and the product ſhall bee 54<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>55, by Rule III, that is gallons 54 and 55 hundreth parts<hi>:</hi> which is the true content ſought for.</p>
                  <p>Although this Gauging inſtrument is properly framed for meaſuring <note place="margin">The uſe of this Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in gauging beere veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells.</note> veſſels by the wine gallon: yet it may alſo fitly be applyed to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring of the ſame veſſels by the ale or beere gallon. And for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe I have on the Ruler figured with digit numbers ſet two little lines or markes, the one at 272¼, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the letter <hi>(w);</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at 231, noted with the letter <hi>(a).</hi> The uſe of which I deliver in this Rule following.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seeke out the content of the veſſell propoſed in wine gallons, upon the ruler figured with denarie numbers, as hath before beene taught: and thereto ſet the marke (w): and ſo ſhall the other marke (a) point to the number of beere gallons contained in the ſame veſſell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:13860:20"/>
I will ſhew the practice of this Rule by the veſſells meaſured in the three laſt examples.</p>
                  <p>Firſt The Canarie pipe, whoſe length was ynches 48<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>5: and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ameter at the bung gallon 0<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>93: and the diameter at the head gallon 0<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>54: the meaſure whereof was by Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple V found to be gallons 116<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>4: how many beere gallons will it containe?</p>
                  <p>Set the marke <hi>(w)</hi> unto the wine meaſure 116<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>4 reconed upon the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler figured with denarie numbers, ſcruing it there faſt, and the marke <hi>(a)</hi> ſhall in the ſame ruler point out 98<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>76 that is gallons 98 and 76 hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth parts, the content thereof in beere meaſure.</p>
                  <p>Againe, The Graves hogſhead, whoſe length was ynches 31<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>2: and the diameter at the bung gallon 0<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>73: and the diameter at the head gallon 0<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>57: the meaſure whereof was by Example VI found to bee gallons 63<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4: how many beere gallons will it containe?</p>
                  <p>Set the marke <hi>(w)</hi> unto the wine
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:13860:21"/>
meaſure 63<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>34 reconed upon the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler figured with denarie numbers, ſcruing it there faſt: and the marke <hi>(a)</hi> ſhall in the ſame Ruler point out 53<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>74, that is gallons 53, and 74 hundreth parts, the content thereof in beere meaſure.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly the High countrey hoggeſ-head, whoſe length was ynches 30<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>82: and the diameter at the bung gallon 0<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>63: and the diameter at the head gallon 0<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>51: the meaſure whereof was by Example VII found to bee gallons 54<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>55: how many beere gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons will it containe?</p>
                  <p>Set the marke <hi>(w)</hi> unto the wine meaſure 54<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5 reconed upon the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler figured with denarie numbers, ſcruing it there faſt: and the marke <hi>(a)</hi> ſhall in the ſame ruler point out 46<g ref="char:decimalL">⌊</g>28, that is gallons 46, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8 hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth parts, the content thereof in beere meaſure.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:13860:21"/>
And now I have finiſhed what I determined to write concerning the uſe of this my <hi>new Gauging line or rod:</hi> and have made it ſo plaine and eaſie that I doubt not but every meane capacitie will bee able with a little care to apprehend the meaning and practice: I have alſo delivered the <hi>Rule</hi> which I follow, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I ground this worke: only the maner of computing the <hi>Gauge-divi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſions</hi> I have concealed: both becauſe that ſpeculation is impertinent to the managing and hand-working there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with: and alſo that becauſe unto men of art by comparing the rule with the performance, it will not bee difficult to find out the reaſon: but eſpecially becauſe I intend and wiſh the benefit of making and fabricating this Inſtrument, unto M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Elias Allen,</hi> who gave the occaſion of it, and at whoſe requeſt I invented it. And if it ſhall bee ſerviceable to this moſt illuſtrious Citie, as a meanes of kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping truth and equitie in that kind, and acceptable to you Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:13860:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
LL, and to you Right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to whom I preſent it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing unto the glory of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, the author of every good abilitie, it hath obtayned the deſired END.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:13860:22"/>
            <p>PErlegi hoc opus Mathematicum, cui titulus eſt, <hi>The new artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Gauging Line or Rod,</hi> in quo nihil reperio quod non cum utilitate publica imprimatur, modò intra tres menſes proximè ſequentes Typis man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Ex aedibus Lambethanis, <date>
                     <hi>Octob.</hi> 10. 1633.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Guil. Bray.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="advert_for_mathematical_instruments">
            <pb facs="tcp:13860:23"/>
            <p>THeſe Inſtruments are made in braſſe by <hi>Elias Allen</hi> over againſt St. <hi>Clements</hi> Church with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Temple-barre: where alſo thoſe who are deſirous may bee inſtructed in the practicall uſe thereof: and ſuch as ſhall have occaſion may have veſſels gauged.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13860:23"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
